<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	 xml:id="pipelines"
         version="5.0">
<info>
  <title>Pipelines</title>
</info>

<para>A pipeline is an acyclic directed graph, a data flow graph describing
how a set of inputs is processed to produce outputs. Processing occurs at nodes
in the graph, data flows along the edges. The simplest nodes are atomic steps: they take
input, perform some operation, and produce output. From the perspective of the pipeline,
these are black boxes.</para>

<para>JAFPL also provides several mechanisms for constructing
compound steps from other steps. These “containers” then become nodes in the
graph that contains them.</para>

<para>There are only a few inviolable constraints on the graph:</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem><simpara>No loops. It’s a
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Directed_acyclic_graph">DAG</link>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Edges can’t cross from inside a container to
outside the container (the children of a container are invisible to
the siblings of the container). Crossing the other direction is
allowed, the children can see their “aunts” and “uncles”.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem><simpara>If steps declare required inputs,
those must have edges connected to them.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem><simpara>Edges can only connect nodes in the same graph.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>Every output port in JAFPL is read by exactly one step and
exactly one step writes to every input port. If the graph described by
your edges multiplexes access to any port, a “splitter” or “joiner”
step will be inserted automatically as appropriate.</para>

<para>In other words, this graph never happens:</para>

<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figure0.svg"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>

<para>If you attempt to construct that graph, the library will automatically
restructure it so that this graph is constructed:</para>

<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figure1.svg"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>

<para>You must provide an
<link xlink:href="../apis/steps">implementation class</link> for every atomic node that you
construct. That’s the class that will be called upon to perform the
work of the step.</para>

<para>The graph is executed with the <link
xlink:href="http://akka.io/">Akka</link> framework. Actors are created
to manage each node. With a few exceptions (conditionals and “catch”
containers, for example), all steps “start” at the same time and
execute in parallel (to the extent that the graph allows for
parallelism, of course). When the last step reports that it is
finished, execution finishes.</para>

<para>The actors know the topology of the graph. Any step that has no
inputs can run immediately. Steps that have inputs can’t run until
all of their inputs have been provided. Inputs pass between the steps
as messages. Consider a simple, linear pipeline:</para>

<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="byhand-1.svg"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>

<para>When execution begins, “Do Something” can’t run because
it’s waiting for input from the “outside”. “Do Something Else” can’t
run because it’s waiting for input from “Do Something.” The process
that is running the pipeline pours an arbitrary number of documents
into the input port. Each document is received immediately by “Do
Something”, which is solely responsible for buffering it or doing
whatever is necessary. Eventually, the process running the pipeline
closes the input port.</para>

<para>At this point, the actor framework tells “Do Something” to run.
It does whatever it does, dropping documents into its output port.
The framework turns those documents into messages that are sent
immediately to “Do Something Else.”</para>

<para>When “Do Something” finishes, the framework closes each of its
output ports and consequently the input port that is reading it. When
the last input port on “Do Something Else” is closed, the framework
tells it to run. And thus it continues until every step has run. When
every step has run, the pipeline is finished. The process running the
pipeline can collect its results from the output port(s).</para>

<para>In practice, there are a number of subtleties here. Loops have
to buffer inputs so that they’re available to each iteration. A choose
must make sure that <emphasis>none</emphasis> of the steps in any of its
branches run before a specific branch is selected. Etc.</para>

<para>This library amends the graph and introduces additional steps as
necessary to hide all of this complexity. Let’s look at
a larger example.
</para>

<para>To illustrate how things work, a small repository of demonstration
pipelines is provided at
<link xlink:href="https://github.com/ndw/jafpl-demo"/>. One of the larger
examples is the “calc” demo. The calc demo application that uses the
library to evaluate simple arithmetic expressions. Using a pipeline
language for this purpose is a bit crazy, but assuming you understand
how arithmetic works, it demonstrates some of the features.</para>

<para>Consider the expression “<code>(1+2)*(3+4+5)</code>”. We don’t often
think of arithmetic as a pipeline, but the expressions <code>(1+2)</code>
and <code>(3+4+5)</code> are independent and could be executed in parallel.
In other words, it’s possible to construct
a pipeline to evaluate this expression:</para>

<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="pipe1.svg"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>

<para>The “Literal” steps are atomic steps that provide numbers. For
convenience, they’re labled “number-<replaceable>n</replaceable>” for
the number “n”. These are simple atomic steps with no inputs and a
single output. When they run, they produce the corresponding number on
their output port.</para>

<para>The expression has been decomposed into a series of binary operations
(3+4+5 = (3+4)+5 because
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Associative_property">addition
is associative</link>). The “BinaryOp” steps perform simple binary arithetic
operations: addition, subtraction, multiplication, and division on two inputs.
</para>

<para>There are no external inputs. When this pipeline starts, the
integer literal steps all execute in parallel, producing one output each.
The additions can also proceed in parallel. Then the multiplication computes
the final sum, “36”, which is output and printed by the demo.</para>

<para>To see what happens when inputs are required, consider this
expression: “<code>(1+2)*$foo</code>”. Here <code>$foo</code> is an
additional input to the expression. Steps have inputs and outputs and
(almost) nothing else.</para>

<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="pipe2.svg"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>

<para>All atomic steps work basically the same way. There’s also a provision for declaring
a dependency edge between two nodes that aren’t connected by data flow. The semantics
of the dependency are that the <emphasis>dependent</emphasis> step will not be run
before the step it <emphasis>depends on</emphasis> has finished.</para>

</article>
